<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Ramblings of an old geek</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Ramblings of an old geek</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Time to update the blog</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/time-to-update-the-blog/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/time-to-update-the-blog/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve looked at my blog from time to time all these years when it&amp;rsquo;s been
laying dormant. I used to be a active blogger years ago but then life got
in the way, I did not have the time for it anymore. At the time I was traveling
more than half the days in a year and updating a blog on the side just
wasn&amp;rsquo;t doable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;vacation-project&#34;&gt;Vacation project&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Finland everyone working a steady job has at least 5 weeks of vacation.
Usually we take 4 weeks in the summer and 1 week in the winter. This year the weather isn&amp;rsquo;t great so I decided one of my summer projects when spending time
inside the house would be getting my blog up and running again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve looked at my blog from time to time all these years when it&rsquo;s been
laying dormant. I used to be a active blogger years ago but then life got
in the way, I did not have the time for it anymore. At the time I was traveling
more than half the days in a year and updating a blog on the side just
wasn&rsquo;t doable.</p>
<h1 id="vacation-project">Vacation project</h1>
<p>In Finland everyone working a steady job has at least 5 weeks of vacation.
Usually we take 4 weeks in the summer and 1 week in the winter. This year the weather isn&rsquo;t great so I decided one of my summer projects when spending time
inside the house would be getting my blog up and running again.</p>
<h2 id="hugo">Hugo</h2>
<p>In 2020 I moved my blog from Wordpress.com to a github and started using Hugo to create the pages. 5 years later I have no idea how I set it up. I tried creating a new page and publishing it to the site but that did not work.</p>
<p>Since I had to relearn the process I decided to go hunting for a nice minimal theme to start form and redo the whole page. This would also allow me to recreate the whole publisihing process and I could refamliarize myself with hugo an the tools I use.</p>
<h2 id="setting-up">Setting up</h2>
<p>If you look at some of my older posts you will see I&rsquo;m running Linux on my home devices and that hasn&rsquo;t changed. I&rsquo;m running Arch Linux (BTW) on my main rig
which is used for most my private computing, be it gaming or small code projects.</p>
<p>To get Hugo running on Arch is easy like most things on Arch. Since the setup
is done and the base theme has been chosen it&rsquo;s time to start modifying the
theme to suit my needs and start recreating some of the still usable blogposts
I had published back when my blog was getting weekly updates.</p>
<p>Even though I&rsquo;m aiming on beeing more active with the writing the reason for writing still aplies. I do it to keep my notes in a place I can easily lookup and have others lookup when needed.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s see what the future brings.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Issues with Coreboot and a workaround</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/coreboot-issues/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 08:09:26 +0300</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/coreboot-issues/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;A while ago I stole the SSD drive from my Lenovo X220 to use it in another
device. The poor X220 has been dormant in storage ever since. This week I finally
had time to install the new drive in it and install Debian testing on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;oops-we-are-not-booting&#34;&gt;Oops we are not booting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installation as with any Debian installation is really straight forward, but
after the installation Coreboot dropped me to the EFI shell instead of booting
the device correctly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while ago I stole the SSD drive from my Lenovo X220 to use it in another
device. The poor X220 has been dormant in storage ever since. This week I finally
had time to install the new drive in it and install Debian testing on it.</p>
<h2 id="oops-we-are-not-booting">Oops we are not booting</h2>
<p>Installation as with any Debian installation is really straight forward, but
after the installation Coreboot dropped me to the EFI shell instead of booting
the device correctly.</p>
<p>Going to duckduckgo for information I found this article on Reddit,<br>
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/linux4noobs/comments/7iwhee/guide_hack_together_a_functioning_efi_boot_using/">https://www.reddit.com/r/linux4noobs/comments/7iwhee/guide_hack_together_a_functioning_efi_boot_using/</a></p>
<p>All the information is in the link, but to make sure I have it available in the future for myself I will document it here as well.</p>
<p>To get the device to boot at all, run the command <em>map</em> in the EFI shell, this will show you all the devices EFI can see.<br>
I did not look at the BLK devices only fsN, in my case fs0 was the correct one. So using that as a base let&rsquo;s kick of the boot.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ fs0:<span class="se">\E</span>FI<span class="se">\d</span>ebian<span class="se">\g</span>rubx64.efi
</span></span></code></pre></div><div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="line"><span class="cl">  $ sudo bash <span class="c1">#enter a root shell</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">  $ mkdir /boot/efi/EFI/BOOT <span class="c1">#create the default directory where coreboot is looking</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">  $ cp /boot/efi/EFI/debian/* /boot/efi/EFI/BOOT/ <span class="c1">#copy the EFI bits to the directory</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">  $ cp /boot/efi/EFI/BOOT/grubx64.efi /boot/efi/EFI/BOOT/bootx64.efi <span class="c1">#copy or rename efi file to bootx64 instead of grubx.</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This will allow you device to boot but with every reset you will have to follow this through. I guess the same goes if you upgrade some of the boot related components, like grub as the updates will not end up in the correct directory. So don&rsquo;t see this as a fix, it&rsquo;s a workaround.<br>
I will continue to look for a more premanent solution for the issue but for now I can boot my X220 and that does lower the urgency of the issue.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Blog moving to GitHub</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/moved-to-github/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 08:09:26 +0300</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/moved-to-github/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the time of year when Wordpress.com is reminding me to renew my subscription
and since I really don&amp;rsquo;t blog as much as I used to back in the days, the price
is just a bit to high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hosting-or-not&#34;&gt;Hosting or not?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started to look for a replacement service, initially I was thinking of hosting
my it on a virtual server somewhere as that&amp;rsquo;s half the price of Wordpress. True
that it would make me manage the server but with ansible that would still be
trivial. First I was looking at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linode.com&#34; title=&#34;Linode&#34;&gt;Linode&lt;/a&gt; as the
cheapest server was only a cup of coffee and this was reasonable for a monthly
price, and on it run Wordpress like I used to when I was really active.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s the time of year when Wordpress.com is reminding me to renew my subscription
and since I really don&rsquo;t blog as much as I used to back in the days, the price
is just a bit to high.</p>
<h2 id="hosting-or-not">Hosting or not?</h2>
<p>I started to look for a replacement service, initially I was thinking of hosting
my it on a virtual server somewhere as that&rsquo;s half the price of Wordpress. True
that it would make me manage the server but with ansible that would still be
trivial. First I was looking at <a href="https://www.linode.com" title="Linode">Linode</a> as the
cheapest server was only a cup of coffee and this was reasonable for a monthly
price, and on it run Wordpress like I used to when I was really active.</p>
<p>As it sometimes happens, curiosity kicked in and I stared digging into static
site generators. And the simplicity they bring was pulling me in. I already
use MarkDown for a lot and looking at <a href="https://gohugo.io" title="Hugo">Hugo</a> made
me even more curious if I could run everything from it.</p>
<p>Done and dusted, easy local installation with <a href="https://brew.sh" title="Homebrew">Brew</a>
was screaming go,go, gooooo.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ brew install hugo
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Now the hosting, should it run on my rented hardware or not. After some
consideration I decided to try Github pages, for now this will be the solution
although I might change that in the future if I want to have a server running
somewhere again.</p>
<h2 id="can-it-be-this-simple">Can it be this simple?</h2>
<p>After installing and initializing my site locally I copied my blogposts from
wordpress to .md files. The simplicity is just amazing. The biggest headache I
had was to find a simple engough theme to use. After some trials I ended up with
<a href="https://themes.gohugo.io/etch/" title="Hugo Etch Theme">Etch</a>. It was simple enough
and I was able to get the few changes done I wanted.</p>
<p>The use of git and Github is also extremely nice, it just fits in my workflow.
Fits like a glove some would say, while we Finns say &ldquo;Fits like a fist in the eye&rdquo;.
I can keep everything with me all the time, and when I change to a new device
everything is seconds away.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Lenovo X220 audio control in i3wm</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/lenovo-x220-and-audio-control-in-i3wm/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 08:09:26 -0700</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/lenovo-x220-and-audio-control-in-i3wm/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;This will serve as a note to myself as I found myself really looking for it
every time I redid the device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lenovo X220 has audio control buttons above the keyboard and they are nice
to have working when using the device.
I use i3-wm myself and I have a old version of my i3 config in my Github,
yes it’s time to update it as well so I don’t have to do this every time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This will serve as a note to myself as I found myself really looking for it
every time I redid the device.</p>
<p>The Lenovo X220 has audio control buttons above the keyboard and they are nice
to have working when using the device.
I use i3-wm myself and I have a old version of my i3 config in my Github,
yes it’s time to update it as well so I don’t have to do this every time.</p>
<p>Anyway, this time the writing is for Debian, I’m using the testing version but
I would assume this works in any of them. First and foremost, I am using the
kernel module thinkpad_acpi and alsa, if you are using pulseaudio you need to
look for the commands for that.</p>
<p>In my i3-config I have the following</p>
<h3 id="audio-setting">Audio setting</h3>
<p>bindsym XF86AudioRaiseVolume exec “amixer -q sset Master,0 1+ unmute”<br>
bindsym XF86AudioLowerVolume exec “amixer -q sset Master,0 1- unmute”<br>
bindsym XF86AudioMute exec “amixer -q sset Master,0 toggle”</p>
<p>Reload your i3 config and you should see the mute led turn on and of as you press it.
Volume up and down works as well.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Adventures in i3 land</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/adventures-in-i3-land/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/adventures-in-i3-land/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;As a geek I do like a lot of the modern things. At work I spend my time working
with device services ranging from cloud services like Intune to things like
traditional printing in factory floors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is very little that get’s me as exited as opening a box with new hardware
in it, but from time to time I feel the hardware improvements are eaten alive
by the ever growing complexity of the software. So while I spend a lot of my
time reading about new things, I also like to go back in time and take a look
at what can be done with older hardware instead of throwing it away.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a geek I do like a lot of the modern things. At work I spend my time working
with device services ranging from cloud services like Intune to things like
traditional printing in factory floors.</p>
<p>There is very little that get’s me as exited as opening a box with new hardware
in it, but from time to time I feel the hardware improvements are eaten alive
by the ever growing complexity of the software. So while I spend a lot of my
time reading about new things, I also like to go back in time and take a look
at what can be done with older hardware instead of throwing it away.</p>
<p>As an example my daughter is using a Mid 2009 MacBook Pro for her needs at the
moment. With an SSD and 8Gb of RAM it works a lot better than expected. I have
a bunch of old ThinkPad’s that have been neglected for quite some time. One of
them being an old X220, and it is the device I’m writing on at the moment.
And speaking of writing, the keyboard on this thing is second to none. I’ve
never typed on a better keyboard than the old Thinkpad’s. They are in my
personal opinion better than any of the current keyboards and so durable.</p>
<p><img src="/images/x220-001.jpg" alt="X220-001"></p>
<p><img src="/images/x220-002.jpg" alt="X220-002"></p>
<p>Considering this device was released in 2011, almost 10 years ago, it still
handles what I throw at it extremely well. I did not try Windows 10 in it
although I think it would have ran decently as well, instead it’s now running
Debian testing with the i3 window manager. A cold boot from entering the
encryption password takes about 7 seconds to the desktop. So even by modern
standards more than decent, in fact a lot faster than my 2018 MacBook Pro and
even faster than my Surface Laptop 3.</p>
<h3 id="i3-window-manager">i3 window manager</h3>
<p>Being fast does come with it’s downsides, if you don’t like them. For me, I
don’t see it as a downside, quite the opposite. As the hardware is older I set
out to use something lightweight. Tiling window managers have fascinated me for
a while now and I thought this hardware could really benefit from one. So
instead of the large WM’s in Linux I decided to go with i3 and for the login
screen Slim DM. Both extremely light and extremely configurable.</p>
<p><img src="/images/x220-scrot-001.png" alt="X220 Screenshot"></p>
<p>Finding your comfort with a tiling window manager might require some work, at
least it did for me. As an example there are things that are so wired in my
brain I have issues trying to change them. One such is the Windows + L key to
lock the computer. My i3 configuration used the VIM keys to move between open
windows, meaning H,J,K,L were bind to that movement. I changed them to the
arrow keys, not perfect, but I do need my Windows + L to lock my session.</p>
<h3 id="slimlock">Slimlock</h3>
<p>As I stated above I use Windows + L to lock my screen. This is something really
wired into my brain, leaving a computer I always do this, needed or not. i3
has this functionality in i3lock and you can call that to lock your screen. I
however wanted to use the same nice GUI that Slim provides me on startup.</p>
<p>I also wanted the system to lock whenever I put my computer to sleep or close
the lid so slimlock had to be called in those cases as well.</p>
<p>My i3 config, contains,</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="line"><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="c1"># Lock screen</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">bindsym <span class="nv">$mod</span>+l <span class="nb">exec</span> “slimlock”
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>and I created the a new file in /etc/systemd/system/i3lock@.service containing;</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-systemd" data-lang="systemd"><span class="line"><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="k">[Unit]</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">Description </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s"> Lock screen when going to sleep/suspend/hibernate</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="k">[Service]</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">User</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">%I</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">Type</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">simple</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">Environment</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">DISPLAY=:0</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">ExecStart</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">/usr/bin/slimlock</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">TimeoutSec</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">infinity</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="k">[Install]</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">WantedBy</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">sleep.target</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">WantedBy</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">suspend.target</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">WantedBy</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">hibernate.target</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The combination works exactly as I want it to.</p>
<h2 id="changes-in-hardware">Changes in hardware</h2>
<p>To make the X220 a bit more modern I added 4Gb of RAM in it. I rarely go over
4Gb in this but still, as I had some laying around I gave it some additional
memory. The time of HDD’s in laptops is long gone as well, so I had a Samsung
860 SSD 1Tb driver on my table I stuffed into the laptop as well. The
combination of the SSD and 8Gb of RAM makes the X220 fly.</p>
<p>Before doing anything else I pulled the whole ting into pieces and replaced the
thermal paste on the CPU, it is as I said 10 years old so it was time to get
this done. If you have ever taken a Lenovo or IBM ThinkPad apart you start to
appreciate the way these things are built. No laptop is easy to pull apart but
with the servicing manuals and no-stress this was a enjoyable moment. I also
notice the fans rarely spool up after applying some Arctic Silver paste on the
CPU and putting everything back together.</p>
<p><img src="/images/x220-003.jpg" alt="X220 maintenance"></p>
<h2 id="can-you-really-do-something-on-it">Can you really do something on it?</h2>
<p>Counting the running laptops and desktops in my house I have 5 of them in daily
use. I really do not work on the X220 but it is able to get things done. I’ve
tried using many of the tools I use in my daily job on it and so far have not
had a single issue or noticeable dip in performance. Microsoft Teams is
probably what I spend the majority of my time collaborating in and it works
flawlessly on this device. I use O365 for email and documents, and although the
web-versions of Word, PowerPoint and Visio are not 1:1 with the desktop
version’s I can still be as effective in them. If I need a Windows desktop I
can even get into one in our Cloud services meaning I really could make this
old-timer my daily driver if I wanted to. And for my job when designing
services for the enterprise, if I can use it from this device then anyone can
use them from whatever they want.</p>
<h2 id="whats-next">What&rsquo;s next?</h2>
<p>I’ve been reading about Coreboot quite a bit, the next step for this old Lenovo
is to get rid of the old BIOS and clear out as much as possible from the Intel
Management Engine, I don’t have to, but I want to. Tinkering is still fun.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Scrolling with an external mouse in MacOS</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/scrolling-with-an-external-mouse-on-macos/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 08:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/scrolling-with-an-external-mouse-on-macos/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have used a Mac with an external mouse you know there is something funky
about this. In MacOS you can not individually select the scroll direction for a
external mouse vs the trackpad. The trackpad when you want to scroll down a page
you basically drag trough it and it’s a very natural motion, this however means
that the scroll wheel on your external mouse will go the opposite way, whoever
came up with this should work on a chair with nails for a few years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you have used a Mac with an external mouse you know there is something funky
about this. In MacOS you can not individually select the scroll direction for a
external mouse vs the trackpad. The trackpad when you want to scroll down a page
you basically drag trough it and it’s a very natural motion, this however means
that the scroll wheel on your external mouse will go the opposite way, whoever
came up with this should work on a chair with nails for a few years.</p>
<p>It’s a totally unnatural way to scroll up on the mouse-wheel when you want to go
down on the page, I mean, WTF.</p>
<p>Anyway, as always some nice folks created an app (I really wish I could do this
in the operating system like any other decent operating system but no, it’s an
app) to reverse the scrolling. You can set it to reverse the trackpad as well
but I guess then you could just have the normal setting for the mouse and the
trackpad would be the opposite. Anyway, let’s not get stuck on this.</p>
<p>I wanted my mouse-wheel to scroll properly as I switch between Windows, Linux
and Mac all the time and I really can’t get my muscle memory to work this way.</p>
<p>Hallelujah, the fix is here, Scroll Reverser. You can either download it from
the the link or if you, like me, use Homebrew you can just run:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ brew cask install scroll-reverser
</span></span></code></pre></div><p><img src="/images/scroll-rev-001.png" alt="Scroll Reverser"></p>
<p>It’s a really really simple app but it makes my life worth living again as I
can scroll up and down the way you should be able to do.</p>
<p>If you do get this and, like me, feel it’s an essential tool to be able to work
with an external mouse (and no, I will not get an external trackpad), then do
not forget to drop the developers a donation. After all, they made life worth
living again.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>MacOS black screen after sleep</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/macos-black-screen-after-sleep/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 06:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/macos-black-screen-after-sleep/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I decided it was time to upgrade my MacBook Pro 2018 from Mojave to
Catalina. Easy update but in the future if someone tells you Windows 10 upgrades
are slow, ask them to try it on a Mac. I can update all Windows devices in my
house one by one faster than my Mac from 10.14 to 10.15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, this was not a post to beat down my Mac, I do still like parts of you 😀&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I decided it was time to upgrade my MacBook Pro 2018 from Mojave to
Catalina. Easy update but in the future if someone tells you Windows 10 upgrades
are slow, ask them to try it on a Mac. I can update all Windows devices in my
house one by one faster than my Mac from 10.14 to 10.15.</p>
<p>Anyhow, this was not a post to beat down my Mac, I do still like parts of you 😀</p>
<p>After the installation was done all was well with my applications, homebrew kept
working and everything appeared to be just fine. Until this morning, like most
mornings I pulled my Mac and opened the lid waiting for the screen to light up,
but no. Touchbar (the worst idea ever by the way) was active but the screen was
black. After my first meetings of the day it was time to test if this still
happened. And yes, it did.</p>
<p>Some digging on the web and someone even had a fix to re-install the operating
system… What the … I’m not going to re-install. Haven’t reinstalled any of my
other computers either and hopefully the Mac is not this unstable that you have
to re-install just for an upgrade when the Windows installations are fine after
years and years of upgrades and Linux installations even more so.</p>
<p>The one common thing I found was that most fixes were deleting .kext files,
kernel extensions. Some even mentioned the specific files to delete, I however
did not have any of them but what I did have on my Mac was the DisplayLink
software as I use it with my Lenovo USB-C docking station. All is fair in war
and computer issues so:</p>
<p>Go to your applications folder and look up DisplayLink,
then run the Uninstaller.</p>
<p>It will ask you to reboot so you should, once done go find the latest driver
from <a href="https://displaylink.com" title="Displaylink">Displaylink.com</a>. Install it, reboot and your black screen should be gone.
This of-course assumes you had DisplayLink installed in the first place :D.</p>
<p>As always the writing here is mostly notes for myself. If you had success with
the above, enjoy and you are welcome.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>MacOS : Unhide dock faster</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/macos-unhide-dock-faster/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 08:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/macos-unhide-dock-faster/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;As I’ve stated I more or less cross paths almost on a daily basis with all the
major operating systems. Most of the time my main driver is the 2018 MacBook Pro
which is with me whenever I leave the comfort of the home-office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the resolution is good on this device the dock at the bottom takes up
a bit of space. I must say I’m not a heavy dock user, I’ve learnt long ago to
use CMD+Space to find my applications, just like I use the Windows key in
Windows 10 and MOD+D in my i3wm on Arch Linux. In my normal configuration I keep
the dock hidden and if you keep the default values you, for a split second,
wonder if it’s coming out at all. So, tweaking it to appear faster felt like a
good idea. Three commands later and we are done. As always, this blog is mostly
so I don’t have to search information on this again and try to find my personal
sweetspot.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I’ve stated I more or less cross paths almost on a daily basis with all the
major operating systems. Most of the time my main driver is the 2018 MacBook Pro
which is with me whenever I leave the comfort of the home-office.</p>
<p>Although the resolution is good on this device the dock at the bottom takes up
a bit of space. I must say I’m not a heavy dock user, I’ve learnt long ago to
use CMD+Space to find my applications, just like I use the Windows key in
Windows 10 and MOD+D in my i3wm on Arch Linux. In my normal configuration I keep
the dock hidden and if you keep the default values you, for a split second,
wonder if it’s coming out at all. So, tweaking it to appear faster felt like a
good idea. Three commands later and we are done. As always, this blog is mostly
so I don’t have to search information on this again and try to find my personal
sweetspot.</p>
<p>Open a terminal and run the following commands, in the following order:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ defaults write com.apple.dock autohide-delay -float <span class="m">0</span>  
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ defaults write com.apple.dock autohide-time-modifier -float 0.5  
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ killall Dock  
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Now it does not feel like the Dock is stuck in mud somewhere, it actually
appears fast enough the few times I really need it.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Hey, where&#39;s my Yubikey?</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/hey-wheres-my-yubikey/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 08:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/hey-wheres-my-yubikey/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is just for myself to remember this as it was behind so many clicks
on the oh so phenomenal &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org&#34; title=&#34;ArchLinux Wiki&#34;&gt;ArchWiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many years I have been using multifactor authentication where possible.
SMS in the beginning and today mostly authenticator application(s) or the
Yubikey(s). These together with a decent password manager make me feel at least
a bit more secure with all the accounts and passwords I need to remember.
If you are looking for a password manager to help make your life a bit laid back
when it comes to password management I recommend you take a look at
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bitwarden.com&#34; title=&#34;Bitwarden Password Manager&#34;&gt;BitWarden&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is just for myself to remember this as it was behind so many clicks
on the oh so phenomenal <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org" title="ArchLinux Wiki">ArchWiki</a>.</p>
<p>For many years I have been using multifactor authentication where possible.
SMS in the beginning and today mostly authenticator application(s) or the
Yubikey(s). These together with a decent password manager make me feel at least
a bit more secure with all the accounts and passwords I need to remember.
If you are looking for a password manager to help make your life a bit laid back
when it comes to password management I recommend you take a look at
<a href="https://bitwarden.com" title="Bitwarden Password Manager">BitWarden</a>.</p>
<h2 id="problems-">Problems &hellip;</h2>
<p>Some nights ago I decided to install Arch Linux on one of my workstations. Easy
and fast installation with a very customizable system, what’s there not to like 😀</p>
<p>Since the system is so highly customizable, you need to read. And I do really
love learning something new, I just have an issue remembering a week down the
line what I did. So that’s why this post is here. This way I can find it fast
the next time I need it.</p>
<p>So, the problem was that my Yubikey did not show up in Firefox. First thing
first you always check dmesg to make sure the device is even recognized.
And so I did,</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="line"><span class="cl">usb 1-2: new full-speed USB device number <span class="m">5</span> using xhci_hcd  
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">usb 1-2: New USB device found, <span class="nv">idVendor</span><span class="o">=</span>1050, <span class="nv">idProduct</span><span class="o">=</span>0120, <span class="nv">bcdDevice</span><span class="o">=</span> 5.02  
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">usb 1-2: New USB device strings: <span class="nv">Mfr</span><span class="o">=</span>1, <span class="nv">Product</span><span class="o">=</span>2, <span class="nv">SerialNumber</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="m">0</span>  
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">usb 1-2: Product: Security Key by Yubico  
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">usb 1-2: Manufacturer: Yubico
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>And there it was. At least my system knew about it. Some
<a href="https://duckduckgo.com" title="DuckDuckGo">duckduckgo.com:fu</a>
later I found an article on
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Firefox/Tweaks#Fido_U2F_authentication" title="ArchWiki Link">ArchWiki Fido U2F authentication</a>
pointing me to the
libu2f-host package. Easy as 1,2,3 fire up pacman install the package and
restart the browser and my Yubikey is back in business.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ sudo pacman -S libu2f-host  
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">resolving dependencies...  
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">looking <span class="k">for</span> conflicting packages...  
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This as stated above is not meant to be a guide on MFA or the Yubikey, just a
placeholder for me to remember what I did if I ever run into it again.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Nixadmins.net back from hiatus</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/nixadmins-back-from-hiatus/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 08:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/nixadmins-back-from-hiatus/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;I can’t believe it’s now 7 years since I was actively posting content. Why? I
started as a Field Engineer at Microsoft and could not find the time nor energy
to keep creating quality content. It’s now a year since I changed my role
starting as an Architect designing the device journey with all that comes with
it. With this role in mind my posts in the future will be different, the content
will be wider than before, meaning I will create posts about the design journeys
and the architectural view as well. But, as I am still me, and deep inside a
geek who loves to tinker with things from A-Z the content will also reflect this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can’t believe it’s now 7 years since I was actively posting content. Why? I
started as a Field Engineer at Microsoft and could not find the time nor energy
to keep creating quality content. It’s now a year since I changed my role
starting as an Architect designing the device journey with all that comes with
it. With this role in mind my posts in the future will be different, the content
will be wider than before, meaning I will create posts about the design journeys
and the architectural view as well. But, as I am still me, and deep inside a
geek who loves to tinker with things from A-Z the content will also reflect this.</p>
<p>In my daily life I’m now more or less in multiple platforms, using Windows,
MacOS and Linux in my daily life. Some posts will be deep in a technology sense
while others might offer you high level views on services I am working on in my
daily life.</p>
<p>I will not commit to a schedule as this site still mostly notes on my personal
ramblings and trying to answer questions I get in my daily life.</p>
<p>First up will be recreation of some of the former posts as I have lost my
backups from my previous site in 2013. Some of them were extremely popular
and I still haven’t found a good  replacement for them.</p>
<p>//Mats</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
